

# Alaric D'Souza

Resident Physican

714-926-4569



alaricdsouza.github.io



orcid: 0000-0002-8744-8136



alaric.dsouza@wustl.edu

### About me ——

Alaric is a Resident Pediatrician in the Boston Combined Residency Program where he cares for pediatric patients at Boston Children's Hospital and Boston Medical Center. He did his MD/PhD at Washington University in St. Louis, and his Computational and Systems Biology dissertation research on Microbial Ecology and antibiotic resistance genes in the Dantas Lab. After residency, Alaric hopes to specialize in Infectious Diseases and lead his own research group studying microbial communities and host-pathogen interactions.

# Skills ——

Software Packages Adobe Illustrator, Adobe Photoshop, EndNote, LaTeX, Microsoft Office

Programming Languages Python, R, Bash, Wolfram Mathematica

Languages English (native) Hindi (beginner)

Computer Hardware, Machining and Fabrication, Welding

# research interests

Microbial ecology, bacterial genomics, and antibiotic resistance.

#### education

2014-22 MD Washington University in St. Louis

2016-20 Dantas Lab, Washington University in St. Louis Computational and Systems Biology

2010-14 Yale University **Ecology and Evolutionary Biology** 

#### research and work experience

2022-pres. Pediatrics Residency **Boston Combined Residency Program** Resident Physician | Medical care for pediatric patients at Boston Children's Hospital and Boston Medical Center.

Dantas Lab 2016-20 Washington University in St. Louis Doctoral Candidate | Ecology of hospital built environment bacteria and infant gut microbiota.

2015 Dantas Lab Washington University in St. Louis Rotation Student | Autologous Fecal Microbial Transplant Analysis

Powell Lab 2012-14 Undergraduate Researcher | Foraging behavior of Aedes aegypti mosquitoes.

2013 Gagneux Lab Swiss Tropical and Public Health Institute Undergraduate Researcher | Antibiotic resistance and mutation rates in Mycobacterium tuberculosis.

2012 Schlesinger Lab The Ohio State University Undergraduate Researcher | Macrophage receptor signaling for Mycobacterium tuberculosis phagosome lysosome fusion escape.

2011 Seva Dhan Mumbai. India Summer Intern | Treatment of alcoholics and drug addicts.

2011 Course Consulting Consultant | Course design for AP Psychology and IB Theory of Knowl-

2009 Mentee of Dr. P.S. Wijewarnasuriya Army Research Labs Summer Intern | Semiconductor photoresist optimization for infrared detectors.

#### [publications]

\* authors contributed equally

2022 Acute and persistent effects of commonly-used antibiotics on the gut microbiome and resistome in healthy adults Anthony WE, Wang B, Sukhum KV, D'Souza AW, Hink T, Cass C, Seiler S, Reske KA, Coon C, Dubberke ER, Burnham CA, Dantas G, Kwon JH Cell Reports | 10.1016/j.celrep.2022.110649

2022 Structural and molecular rationale for the diversification of resistance mediated by the Antibiotic\_NAT family Stogios PJ, Bordeleau E, Xu Z, Skarina T, Evdokimova E, Chou S, Diorio-Toth L, D'Souza AW, Patel S, Dantas G, Wright GD, Savchenko A Communications Biology | 10.1038/s42003-022-03219-w

2021 Destination shapes antibiotic resistance gene acquisitions, abundance increases, and diversity changes in Dutch travelers. D'Souza AW\*, Boolchandani M\*, Patel S, Galazzo G, Hattem J, Arcilla M, Melles D, Jong M, Schultsz C, Dantas G, Penders J

Genome Medicine | 10.1186/s13073-021-00893-z

2021	Manure microbial communities and resistance profiles reconfigure after transition to manure pits and differ from fertilized field soil
	Sukhum K, Vargas R, D'Souza AW, Boolchandani M, Patel S, Kesaraju A, Walljasper G, Hedge H, Ye Z, Valenzuela R, Gunderson P, Bendixsen C, Dantas G, Shukla S <i>mBio</i>   10.1128/mBio.00798-21
2020	Environmental remodeling of human gut microbiota and antibiotic resistome in livestock farms Sun J*, Liao XP*, D'Souza AW*, Boolchandani M*, Li SH*, Cheng K, Martinez JL, Li L, Feng YJ, Fang LX, Huang T, Xia J, Yu Y, Zhou YF, Sun YX, Deng XB, Zeng ZL, Jiang HX, Fang BH, Tang YZ, Lian XL, Zhang RM, Fang ZW, Yan QL, Dantas G, Liu YH  Nature Communications   10.1038/s41467-020-15222-y
2019	Genomic characterization of antibiotic resistant <i>Escherichia coli</i> isolated from domestic chickens in Pakistan Rafique M*, Potter RF*, Ferreiro A, Wallace MA, Rahim A, Malik AA, Siddique N, Abbas MA, D'Souza AW, Burnham CD, Ali N, Dantas G <i>Frontiers in Microbiology</i>   10.3389/fmicb.2019.03052
2019	Cotrimoxazole prophylaxis increases resistance gene prevalence and $\alpha$ -diversity but decreases $\beta$ -diversity in the gut microbiome of HIV-exposed, uninfected infants. D'Souza AW*, Moodley-Govender E*, Berla B, Kelkar T, Wang B, Sun X, Daniels B, Coutsoudis A, Trehan I, Dantas G Clinical Infectious Diseases   10.1093/cid/ciz1186
2019	Breakpoint beware: reliance on historical breakpoints for Enterobacteriaceae leads to discrepancies in interpretation of susceptibility testing for carbapenems and cephalosporins and gaps in detection of carbapenem-resistant organisms.  Yarbrough ML, Wallace MA, Potter RF, D'Souza AW, Dantas G, Burnham CD  European Journal of Clinical Microbiology & Infectious Diseases   10.1007/s10096-019-03711-y
2019	Spatiotemporal dynamics of multidrug resistant bacteria on intensive care unit surfaces. D'Souza AW*, Potter RF*, Wallace M, Shupe A, Patel S, Sun X, Gul D, Kwon JH, Andleeb S, Burnham CD, Dantas G Nature Communications   10.1038/s41467-019-12563-1
2019	Phenotypic and genotypic characterization of linezolid resistant <i>Enterococcus faecium</i> from the USA and Pakistan.  Wardenburg K*, Potter R*, D'Souza AW, Hussain T, Wallace M, Andleeb A, Burnham CA, Dantas G <i>Journal of Antimicrobial Chemotherapy</i>   10.1093/jac/dkz367
2019	Sequencing-based methods and resources to study antimicrobial resistance.  Boolchandani M*, D'Souza AW*, Dantas G  Nature Reviews Genetics   10.1038/s41576-019-0108-4
2018	Infant diet and maternal gestational weight gain predict early metabolic maturation of gut microbiomes. Baumann-Dudenhoeffer AM, D'Souza AW, Tarr PI, Warner BB, Dantas G Nature Medicine   10.1038/s41591-018-0216-2
2018	Superficieibacter electus gen. nov., sp. nov., an Extended-Spectrum $\beta$ -Lactamase Possessing Member of the Enterobacteriaceae Family, Isolated From Intensive Care Unit Surfaces. Potter RF*, D'Souza AW*, Wallace MA, Shupe A, Patel S, Gul D, Kwon JH, Beatty W, Andleeb S, Burnham CD, Dantas G Frontiers in Microbiology   10.3389/fmicb.2018.01629
2017	Draft Genome Sequence of the <i>bla</i> OXA-436- and <i>bla</i> NDM-1-Harboring <i>Shewanella putrefaciens</i> SA70 Isolate. Potter RF*, D'Souza AW*, Wallace MA, Shupe A, Patel S, Gul D, Kwon JH, Andleeb S, Burnham CD, Dantas G <i>Genome Announcements</i>   10.1128/genomeA.00644-17
2016	The rapid spread of carbapenem-resistant Enterobacteriaceae.  Potter RF*, D'Souza AW*, Dantas G  Drug Resistance Updates   10.1016/j.drup.2016.09.002
2014	Malignant cancer and invasive placentation: A case for positive pleiotropy between endometrial and malignancy phenotypes.  D'Souza AW and Wagner GP  Evolution, Medicine, and Public Health   10.1093/emph/eou022

#### published abstracts

published	abstracts
2021	Microbiome and immune disruption accompany mouse death in a gnotobiotic mouse model of neonatal sepsis
	Schwartz D, Wardenburg K, Shalon N, Ning J, Crofts T, D?Souza A, Robinson J, Henderson J, Warner B, Tarr P, Dantas G
	Journal of the Pediatric Infectious Diseases Society   10.1093/jpids/piab031.010
2020	The Gut Microbiome and Resistome of Healthy Volunteers are Restructured After Short Courses of Antibiotics Anthony W, Sukhum K, Cass C, Reske K, Seiler S, Hink T, Coon C, D'Souza A, Wang B, Sun S, Dubberke E, Burnham C-A, Dantas G, Kwon JH  Infection Control & Hospital Epidemiology   10.1017/ice.2020.476
2017	
2017	Longitudinal Analysis of ICU Surface Multidrug-resistant Organism Contamination in the US and Pakistan Kwon JH, D'Souza A, Potter R, Wallace M, Shupe A, Patel S, Gul D, Andleeb S, Burnham C-A, Dantas G Open Forum Infectious Diseases   10.1093/ofid/ofx163.245
2015	Autologous Fecal Microbiota Transplantation as a Strategy to Prevent Colonization With Multidrug-Resistant Organisms Following Antimicrobial Therapy
	Bulow C, D'Souza A, Hink T, Wallace M, Reske K, Sun X, Kwon JH, Burnham C-A, Dantas G, Dubberke E Open Forum Infectious Diseases   10.1093/ofid/ofv133.479
invited ta	lks
2021	6 mo M presenting with 5 days of fever, emesis, and irritability BJC/SLCH Infectious Diseases Grand Rounds
2021	An exploration of Emergency Department turnaround time data WUSTL Clinical Informatics Seminar
2021	Total thyroidectomy in a 15 yo F with familial adenomatous polyposis WUSTL GI Seminar
2021	Angiomyolipoma in a 9 yo F with tuberous sclerosis WUSTL Pathology Seminar
2020	16S rRNA gene sequencing in bacterial endocarditis WUSTL Lab Medicine Seminar
2019	Effects of antibiotic prophylaxis on the HIV-exposed uninfected infant gut microbiome WUSTL MSTP Work in Progress Seminar
2018	Bacterial contamination on hospital ICU surfaces in the United States and Pakistan WUSTL Microbiology Department Seminar

	American Society of Microbiology Micro
2017	Bacterial contamination on hospital ICU surfaces in the United States and Pakista

Bacterial contamination on hospital ICU surfaces in the United States and Pakistan CSB-MMMP-PMB Interdepartmental Retreat

2017 Multidrug resistant organisms on hospital surfaces in the United States and Pakistan

Computational and Systems Biology Retreat

2017 Longitudinal analysis of ICU surface microbial contamination in the United States and Pakistan

American Society of Microbiology Micro

2017 Effects of trimethoprim-sulfamethoxazole on the microbiomes of HIV- infants born to HIV+ mothers

Bacterial contamination on hospital ICU surfaces in the United States and Pakistan

Bacterial contamination on hospital ICU surfaces in the United States and Pakistan

**WUSTL Center for Genome Sciences** 

**WUSTL Center for Genome Sciences** 

2017 Antibiotic Resistance: a growing public health crisis

WUSTL Institute of Public Health

2013 Drop Team and Rayleigh-Taylor instability

Canyon High School AP biology class

2012 Mannose Receptor Signaling

**SUCCESS** 

2018

2018

#### patents

2018 Store-Easy Automotive wheelchair storage device.

Patent US9937088B2

Guertler C, D'Souza AW, Milgrom R, Hong T, Xiao Y, Nadell S

#### posters

2019	Spatiotemporal dynamics of multidrug resistant bacteria on intensive care unit surfaces.

IMM/MICRO Mini WIP

2019 Cotrimoxazole prophylaxis increases resistance gene prevalence and  $\alpha$ -diversity but decreases  $\beta$ -diversity

in the gut microbiome of HIV-exposed, uninfected infants.

American Society of Microbiology (ASM) Microbe

2019 Longitudinal analysis of ICU surface microbial contamination in the US and Pakistan

NIAID/IDSA Infectious Diseases Research Careers Meeting

2018 Longitudinal Analysis of ICU Surface Microbial Contamination in the US and Pakistan

American Physician Scientist Association (APSA) Midwest meeting

2018 Longitudinal Analysis of ICU Surface Microbial Contamination in the US and Pakistan

Lake Arrowhead Microbial Genomics Conference

2018 Longitudinal Analysis of ICU Surface Microbial Contamination in the US and Pakistan

American Society of Microbiology (ASM) Microbe

2017 Longitudinal Analysis of ICU Surface Microbial Contamination in the US and Pakistan

American Society of Microbiology (ASM) Microbe

2017 Longitudinal Analysis of ICU Surface Microbial Contamination in the US and Pakistan

5th annual Global Health & Infectious Disease Conference

2014 Invasive populations of Aedes aegypti in Central California

Yale Ecology and Evolutionary Biology Poster Session

The genetics of foraging behavior in *Aedes aegypti* 

Cell Symposia: Genes, Circuits, and Behavior

2012 Mannose receptor signaling linking spleen tyrosine kinase and MAP kinase p38 in human macrophages

The Ohio State University SUCCESS program

2009 Relationship of spinning time and speed to photoresist thickness on semiconductor wafers

Army Research Labs: Science and Engineering Apprentice Program

#### [awards]

2022	_	· ·	0 1	A I		D 1: 1 :
2022	Η.	Sessions	Cole	Award	ın	Pediatrics

2022 Alexander Berg Prize

2022 Washington University Internal Medicine Club Research Award

2021 Gold Humanism Honor Society Inductee

2020 Spencer T. and Ann W. Olin Fellow

2017-18 Burroughs Wellcome Fund, Institutional Program Unifying Population and Laboratory-Based Sciences

2016 BioEnterpreneurship Core Bench to Business Competition

2015 IDEA Labs Demo Day Finalist

2013 Alan S. Tetelman Fellowship for International Research in the Sciences

2013 Paul K. and Evelyn Elizabeth Cook Richter Fellowship

2013 Connecticut Space Grant College Consortium Student Project Grant

2012 CBC Spouses Cheerios Brand Health Initiative Scholarship

2011 CBC Louis Stokes Health Scholarship2010 CBC Louis Stokes Health Scholarship

## professional memberships

2021-pres. Gold Humanism Honor Society

2019-pres. Infectious Diseases Society of America2016-pres. American Society for Microbiology

# teaching

2017-20	Computational Teaching Assistant   Fundamentals of Biostatistics   Washington University in St. Louis
2017-20	Graduate Mentor   Visiting scholars, rotation students, and undergraduates   Dantas Lab
2017	Teaching Assistant   Microbes and Pathogenesis   Washington University in St. Louis
2017	Graduate Mentor   IPH Summer Program   Washington University in St. Louis
2016	Graduate Mentor   Eureka Program   Washington University in St. Louis
2013-14	Lecturer   Origins of Life   Yale Splash
2011-14	Lecturer   The Science of Ice Cream   Yale Splash

2011-14	Lecturer   The Science of Ice Cream   Yale Splash
activities	and leadership
2020	Volunteer Maker Task Force, Washington University in St. Louis/Barnes Jewish Hospital Helped produce face shields for hospital
2019-pres.	Volunteer Saturday Neighborhood Health Clinic Seeing patients as a medical student volunteer for the free clinic
2014-pres.	Yale Admissions Interviewer  Interviewer for Yale College admissions of prospective undergraduate students  Yale Alumni Schools Committee
2015-17	Physicians for Human Rights  Co-President of club focusing on human rights and political issues that relate to medicine, including health-care for prisoner, refugees, and underserved communities
2014-17	Store-Easy Washington University in St. Louis - Sling Health Company seeking to improve manual wheelchair storage in automobiles
2012-14	NASA Microgravity University (Drop Team)  Undergraduate research team selected by NASA to conduct fluid mechanics research in zero-gravity
2012-14	Splash at Yale Undergraduate group teaching short courses to middle and high school students
2011-14	Big Sib  Mentor to freshman students at Yale University  Yale University - Pierson College